<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to the flock professing the true light which lighteth every one that cometh into the world : wherein the opposers and villifiers of the true light are (by the way) expostulated with, and they that own it are exhorted to answer the light in the consciences of others by an unblamable light, and to grow up therein, both in general and in their particular relations : given forth chiefly for the service of some in the flock and may be serviceable also to others / from W.T.</title>
            <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62897</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T1847</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R26323</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">09427822</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 09427822</idno>
            <idno type="VID">43059</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62897)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 43059)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1318:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to the flock professing the true light which lighteth every one that cometh into the world : wherein the opposers and villifiers of the true light are (by the way) expostulated with, and they that own it are exhorted to answer the light in the consciences of others by an unblamable light, and to grow up therein, both in general and in their particular relations : given forth chiefly for the service of some in the flock and may be serviceable also to others / from W.T.</title>
                  <author>Tomlinson, William.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Pastoral letters and charges.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:43059:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN EPISTLE TO THE FLOCK, PROFESSING The true Light which lighteth every one that cometh into the World:</p>
            <p>Wherein the Oppoſers and Villifiers of the True Light are (by the way) Expoſtulated with.</p>
            <p>And they that own it are exhorted to Anſwer the Light in the Conſciences of others by an unblamable life, and to grow up therein, both in the general, and in their particular Relations.</p>
            <p>Given forth chiefly for the Service of ſome in the Flock, and may be ſerviceable alſo to others.</p>
            <p>From a Lover of Truth and Righteouſneſs, whereſoever it is found. <hi>W. T.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1674.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:43059:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:43059:2"/>
            <head>AN EPISTLE to the FLOCK, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing the true Light which lighteth every one that cometh into the World, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>AS it pleaſed the Lord formerly to open my Mouth to check the Inſultings of the firſt Adverſary that appeared in Print againſt this preſent Diſpenſation, to have ſlain it in its Infancy; and afterwards to reprove the fraternity of thoſe who ſtood under the name of Prieſts, crying out againſt all that with-drew from them as <hi>Hereticks</hi> and <hi>Seducers,</hi> &amp;c. So now it hath pleaſed him to open my Mouth to ſpeak to ſome in the Flock gathered in under the acknowledgment of, and teſtimony to, the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the World; yet not in that manner as I ſpake to the former, who appeared as open Adverſaries, but in tenderneſs and love, to admoniſh and to help forward the work of the Lord in the ſpirits of ſome, and to ſtir them up to mind the weighty things which the Lord chiefly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires in the Life and Converſation.</p>
            <p>For let none think it ſufficient that they are gathered into an out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Profeſſion of any Truth, or into this Society: But conſider and underſtand that the Kingdom of Heaven is like a Net caſt into the Sea, which gathers of every kind, ſome good, ſome bad. So it was in the Primitive, or firſt gathering after Chriſt, and ſo it is now: Some gathered then, that were to be caſt away; and we may ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect the ſame things now, <hi>Math.</hi> 13.19. <hi>So ſhall it be</hi> (ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord) <hi>in the end of the World, The Angels ſhall come forth, and ſhall ſever the Evil Ones out of the midſt of the Righteous, and ſhall caſt them into a Furnace of fire, there ſhall be weeping and gnaſhing of teeth,</hi> ver. 50. So that although there hath been a ſeparation from other Societies, and from the World, yet it remains that every one make
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:43059:3"/>their Calling and Election ſure, that they purge out the evil that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains unpurged away out of the heart, till they become blameleſs and without offence in the World, and bear ſo lively a Character of the Innocency of Chriſt our Lord, that all that ſee, and certainly know their Lives and Converſations, may ſay of them, <hi>This is the Seed which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Dear Friends, you have been called to the teſtimony of a preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Truth, if you rightly underſtand it, and abide therein. And though it hath many oppoſers, yea, and ſuch as think of themſelves highly, as above ſo low a Doctrine; yet it will ſtand when they ſhall fall. And although they vilifie it, and would reproach it with the terms of natural light, and common light; yet it will diſcover their darkneſs in their traditional
<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>That is, Doctrinal Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Principles received by tradition one from another, which they follow as their light and guide (as the</hi> Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees <hi>did.) This being dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, is great darkneſs, holding them faſt which ſtick therein.</hi>
               </note> which they receive upon truſt one from another. What if the Light that lighteth every man that cometh into the World, be a common Light? Is it the worſe for that? Is the Sun the leſs excellent, becauſe it gives light to all? or its light the leſs precious becauſe it ſhines upon all? Is the Rain the worſe becauſe it falls upon the Bad as well as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Good? No more is the true Light the leſs precious, becauſe of the commonneſs of it, for that may in ſome ſenſe be called common which lights every man; even as that Power is common which gives motion unto all, in which we live &amp; move. Thou that oppoſes it, it may be thou profeſſes a light above it, as thou thinkeſt. Well, but for all that take heed that this diſcover not thy Nakedneſs, even as Chriſt Jeſus, that Light of the World, diſcovered the Nakedneſs of the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees</hi> by the common Actions of their Life, ſuch as were obvious to all. Take heed that this common Light diſcover not in thee, Pride of heart as was in the Phariſees: Exaltedneſs of mind from an out-ſide Profeſſion, as was in them, or Covetouſneſs under a Cloak of Religion, or Earthly-mindedneſs, or Self-willed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, or Hard heartedneſs, or Crafty Policy to circumvent or get beyond another, or Fierceneſs, or Implacableneſs, or Contentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and ſuch like. For verily the common light in all men will manifeſt ſuch things to them; and then thy covering of thy ſelf with thy more excellent light, as thou thinks is become too narrow for thee, and will not hide thy nakedneſs from the world, who have but that common light, as thou in diſdain calls it. For if they ſee a
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:43059:3"/>haughty ſpirit in thee, will not they count of thee as thou art, A Proud Man? And their judgment and repute of thee is true, and will ſtand, being guided by the true light which diſcovers thee to them by thy fruits. So if thou art a Covetous perſon, the light diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covers thee to the World. Yea, by common and true Light, men are made manifeſt one to another where they live, and where their actions are well known. And therefore they can ſee, and ſay one to another, ſuch a man is a hard-hearted man; and again, ſuch a one is a tender-hearted merciful man. What! do they ſee the heart? Doth the common Light diſcover the heart? Yea, by the fruits it diſcovers it: Therefore they can ſay (diſcerning by the light) ſuch a perſon is Zealous for his way of Religion, but I ſhould be loath to fall into his hands; I durſt not truſt him for all his Profeſſion. Such a perſon, it's true, he will not abuſe himſelf with Drink, but he is Drunk with his own conceits. And again of another they can ſay, Such a man is a faithful truſty man, I durſt commit any thing I have into his hands without fear. Thus the Lord diſcovers Trees by the Fruits, Men by their Actions, and the common Light receives as well as gives the diſcovery. And of this many Friends have much experience, whoſe faithfulneſs and uprightneſs hath ſuch teſtimony in the hearts of their Neighbours, that they dare truſt them with all they have, when they dare not truſt their own Relations and Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. On the other ſide, are there not ſome (I ſpeak it with grief) whom the World will not truſt, though under the ſame outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Truth? Why? Becauſe they ſee them in the ſame Nature with others that will over-reach. So that no outward profeſſion of Truth can hide from the common Light. Therefore the Light, that common Light is precious (even as the common Salvation is preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous) to the Profeſſion of which you are called; and under the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment of which you have been gathered. And therefore abide therein, and ſo walk as to anſwer that Light in every mans Conſcience. And think it not ſufficient that you are gathered out of ſeveral Societies, and out of the World, under the Profeſſion hereof, except you walk therein. He that walketh therein, he is blameleſs before men; they have no evil thing to ſay of him juſtly. For its by the Life and Converſation among men, that a man is accounted an Innocent man, or an evil doer; and its by the Light that he is ſeen to be ſo. He therefore that doth not in his Life and Converſation anſwer the common Light that is in all men, he is not therein right before the Lord, who hath ſet up that Light in every Man to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern by.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:43059:4"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> It may be thou wilt ſay, <hi>But we find by experience that many good men are evil ſpoken of by the World, and Reproached, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted good men, though they be ſo; the judgment therefore of the World is falſe concerning many Righteous and Godly perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> I Anſwer: Firſt, mind that thou thy ſelf doſt not judge wrong of men, and count thoſe Godly perſons who are not. Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der whether their Godlineſs lye only or chiefly in an outward Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion and Zeal of their way of Worſhip, and for that Society that they are of: If ſo, then their judgment who judge by the Life and Converſation, may be right, and thine wrong; as Chriſts was right concerning the Phariſees, and others wrong who only lookt at their high Profeſſion and ſtrickt obſervation of pious obſervances, as they were reputed.</p>
            <p>Secondly: But if the perſons Reproached be Innocent in Life, juſt and merciful men, then thoſe that know them well will ſcarcely ſpeak evil of them (except in the matters of their God,) unleſs the common light in them be obſtructed and darkened by ſome means, as by ſome private concern, or through malice and enmity in their hearts; or by prejudice, judging by the hearing of the ear, which is often unrighteous judgment, or through ſome particular traditional Light, which is darkneſs. Theſe and ſuch like things pervert true judgment, even as the Light of the Sun ſhining thorow glaſs gives the colour of the glaſs upon the oppoſite Object: So they that judge through theſe things, give judgment according to thoſe falſe <hi>mediums</hi> they judge thorow. But theſe ſtand not in ſo doing in the common Light, but in a perverting light, which is darkneſs; and this their judgment is judged to be falſe by thoſe that ſtand unbyaſſed in the common Light with them; and the very ground of that their falſe judging is often ſeen by them. So that the unbyaſſed common Light is ſtill a true judge in the common actions of mens Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> It may be thou wilt further Object. <hi>That this Light is but a natural Light, and a natural Light is not a true judge, no more than the natural Man which cannot perceive the things of the Spirit of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Where the Apoſtle uſes thoſe words, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. He is there ſpeaking of the things which God hath prepared for them that love him, <hi>ſuch as Eye hath not ſeen, nor Ear heard</hi> (but not of the things that appertain to the common life of man, and are viſible be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all men) and ſuch things indeed are not known but by a farther
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:43059:4"/>Revelation in the Light and Spirit of God which ſearcheth all things, even the deep things of God. However the common open Life of men is ſeen and judged by the common Light (as thou calls it) that God hath planted in every man. And if thou wilt call that Light Natural, yet will that nothing at all advantage thee, whoſoever thou art that walks contrary to it; but it doth the more aggravate thy fault that thou lives contrary to a Light which God hath made ſo na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural to thee, and ſo planted in thee, that thou canſt do no evil but it diſcovers it in thee, yea, and records it in thy Conſcience, as in a Book. And there's the Book that is to be opened when the judgment is ſet, and thou comes to be judged. And the things written in that Book, are the things done in the body, whether good or bad, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to them thou ſhalt be judged. And then this Light which thou calls Natural, and was privy to all thy actions, yea, and to the intents and thoughts of thy heart, will be a Witneſs againſt thee, and ſhew thee thy evil deeds written in thy own Conſcience, and ſo God will be cleared when he comes to Judge, and all the world ſhall be convinced thereby that they are guilty.</p>
            <p>If thou calleſt that Light Common or Natural in an evil ſignificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if it were no true Light, but a deceitful, deluſive, unclean Light, and a Product of the falne Nature, then I ſhall not admit of thoſe terms at all, for then muſt it incline thee to evil of its own Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture (as falſe Lights do) and not ſtand as a diſcoverer of evil in thee, and a faithful and true Witneſs againſt it. Then alſo ſhould it be a thing to be repented of; that is, to have the mind turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from it, and the actions of the life carryed contrary to it, if it be evil and deluſive. And ſo when it checks thee ſecretly in thy heart for Swearing or Lying, or wrong dealing, or any other evil action or purpoſe of thy heart, thou ſhould'ſt then the rather do them, becauſe they are contrary to this deceitful and deluſive Light (as its accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thee) and ſo more likely to be true and good than it. Or at leaſt Wiſe, thou ſhouldſt not at all thereby be moved to avoid thoſe evils, becauſe its but a ſinful evil deluſive light that would ſtop thy carreer in them. Again, if that light be evil then its from the falne Nature, and ſo from Satan that works therein, And then is Satans Kingdom divided, and he by that light ſeeks to bring to nought his own Kingdom. For that Light works againſt his Kingdom in men: It works to throw down Hypocriſie and Deceit, and Lying, and Swearing, and Drunkenneſs, and Uncleanneſs, and Wrath, and Envy, and Murther, and all ſuch evil diſpoſitions and actions, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:43059:5"/>Satans Kingdom ſtands, by diſcovering theſe things to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to be evil, and witneſſing againſt them; and ſo Satan is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided againſt himſelf, if this Light be evil and from him. See what Conſequences thy oppoſing of thy ſelf to the Scripture of truth puts thee upon. Had'ſt thou not better ſubmit to the Teſtimony of the Servant of the Lord, who ſaid <hi>That was the true Light which lighteth every man that cometh into the World?</hi> Be aſhamed to ſay the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is thy rule when thou fights againſt it, and ſays contrary to it. It ſaith, <hi>That was the true Light which lighteth every man that cometh into the World:</hi> Thou faiſt, it is not. How is it thy rule now, when thou denys, or oppoſes it? Laſtly, let this ſink into thy heart, O vain Contender, who ſtrives againſt the Truth: Wilt thou make that to be evil, which leads, or directs into the paths of Peace? and in following of which, even ſome of the Gentiles have found an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing Conſcience? and if that excuſe, we have Peace with God; and for want of following it, how many call'd Chriſtians dye in hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, ſuch as glory in their Chriſtianity over the Heathen Unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers? But tell me, ſhall not their Obeying that Light be accounted to them for Chriſtianity, when thy diſobeying it ſhall be counted to thee Paganiſme and Gentiliſme, although thou glories over them? Even as formerly the Uncircumciſion of ſuch who kept the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſne's of the Law was counted to them for Circumciſion; and the Circumciſion of ſuch as kept it not was accounted for Uncircumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. What did the name of Circumciſion profit them that were Tranſgreſſors and Evil doers under the Law? And what will the name of Chriſtianity profit thee who walks contrary to the Light that diſcovers ſin and wickedneſs in thee? Therefore own that Light that enlightens every mans Conſcience, and ſubmit to it in thy life, and in thy words; own it in thy actions as well as in thy expreſſions; and bring thy deeds to the Light, and weigh them in the Light, that they may be made manifeſt that they are wrought in God. And thou haſt alſo the harmony and conſent of the Writings of the holy men of God, concurring with that Light in thee, to make the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of it the ſtronger in thee againſt all ungodlineſs and worldly Luſts. Therefore if thou, who art called a Chriſtian, walks contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to it, the greater will be thy Condemnation; the preventing of which is the thing to be minded by thee, and not jangling about the Light in words, whilſt thou diſobeys it in practice.</p>
            <p>If thou wilt needs call it natural &amp; common, &amp; yet own it from the Lord, then I matter not that thy calling it ſo; pleaſe thy ſelf in thy
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:43059:5"/>own terms; but know <hi>That it is a Beam from the infinite Majeſty,</hi> which hath no fellowſhip with wickedneſs, but diſcovers it, reproves it, and is contrary to it: And by the teſtimony of it in thy ſelf, and in all men, will the Lord be clear when he judges the world in Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs.</p>
            <p>I further affirm againſt thee that undervalues this light, that there is ſuch a piercing ſight in it, that thereby the true Seed is known and diſcerned by all that ſee them thorowly; as it is ſaid in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecy of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> chap. 61.9. <hi>All that ſee them ſhall acknowledg them, that they are the Seed which the Lord hath bleſſed.</hi> He had been ſpeaking a little before of the <hi>Meek,</hi> the <hi>Broken-hearted,</hi> the <hi>Mourners</hi> in <hi>Zion,</hi> ſuch as were under a <hi>Spirit of heavineſs,</hi> ſuch as our Lord comforted, and Preached good tydings to, pronouncing them bleſſed, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. (as was Propheſied of him to do, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.1.) That Innocent Seed, whoſe meek, quiet, humble temper, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>offenſive ſpirit, whoſe blameleſs life whoſoever ſhall ſee, they ſhall be thereby convinced in their hearts, That this is the Seed which God hath bleſſed: This Convincement ſeeing it ſhall be upon all that ſee them, it muſt needs be from a light common to them all, which is the true Light. If any oppoſe this, let them ſhew from whence it ſhall be that all that ſee them ſhall have this diſcovery of them. This teſtimony, I ſay the common Light will give of them in all mens hearts that ſee and know them in truth. I ſhall not deny but that ſome may judge otherwiſe, even of the true Seed thorow ſiniſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, and prejudicate received opinion, or by judging thorow re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived traditional Notions, or by the hearing of the ear, or by judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing according to other mens judgments, or being ſwayed by ſome private concern, or judging by imagination and ſuch like falſe ways of judging, eſpecially they that are of a Phariſaical Spirit, exalted in the formal part of any Religious Profeſſion, and judging thorow that; theſe not judging in the common true Light that lightens every man that cometh into the world, may eaſily give a falſe judgment of the true Seed, whilſt thoſe whom they deſpiſe, as having no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, may judge rightly of them; and ſometimes even their own Conſciences may (from the common Light at preſent overſwayed in them) lay up in them at the bottom that which ſhall force them in due time to confeſs to the true Seed, and that they mght have ſeen them if they had not hearkened to thoſe falſe wayes of judging; ſo that ſtill I ſay, the unbyaſſed common Light that enlightens every man, is the true Light; and theſe particular Lights, through which the falſe judgment proceeds are not the true Light.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:43059:6"/>
            <p>Well then, If this be the true Light, let every one that Profeſſes it, mind to anſwer this Light in every mans Conſcience. This you have been often exhorted to do by thoſe who have laboured with you in the truth, and there may be need ſtill to put you in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance thereof, that ſo the actions of your life may be approved of by all that know you, though they cannot approve of your way or Religion, as they uſe to ſpeak. And conſider that herein you ſtand as the lights of the world, even in your Actions, in your Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in your Works: Therefore ſaith our Lord, <hi>Let your Light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good Works,</hi> and glorifie your Father which is in Heaven. It is not talking good words, without living a good life that glorifies God. It's the Life, the Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that's approved or diſapproved in other mens Conſciences. It's that which gathers to Chriſt, or being amiſs, ſcatters from him. Profeſs what thou wilt, and with what eagerneſs thou wilt, as if thou wert Zealous for him; yet if Wickedneſs be found in thee, thou doſt but harden mens hearts againſt the truth, and gathers not into the life of truth. If they ſee unfaithfulneſs in thee, that thou haſt more reſpect to thy own ends, than to ſingle truth; minds thy own gain more than ſimple honeſty; makes uſe of advantages from ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers weakneſs, or ignorance, or tenderneſs, to get beyond him; this will be ſeen that it is not right in the ſight of the Lord; and the Light in others will judge it, and thou doſt not approve thy ſelf to their Conſciences. And though thou maiſt ſmooth over thy action artificially with words, and make fair pretences, yet that doth not make thee approved in their Conſciences. Thou maiſt ſtop their tongues perhaps from clamour, but thou doſt not ſatisfie their minds and Conſciences. For <hi>It's the voyce of thy Actions, not of thy Words that takes place in their hearts.</hi> And therefore there is no approving of thy ſelf to their Conſciences, nor anſwering of the true Light in them, but by thy faithful, honeſt, ſingle, upright actions. And as thou approveſt thy ſelf to their Conſciences, ſo thou begers in them the like eſteem of others. If thou art of a haughty, lofty ſpirit, and deſpifeſt others, as the Phariſees did, they think all are ſo, until they find it otherwiſe by experience and tryal of ſome. But if thou be humble, meek, lowly-minded, down-right honeſt, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to be truſted, and thy Word as a Rock to be built upon, as it ought to be; then thou honours what thou profeſſes, and them that profeſſe the ſame truth with thee. If thou art a Buſie-body, going about tatling of others, and deſcanting upon them and their actions,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:43059:6"/>and ſo ſowing Enmity and Diſaffection in the minds of people to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards one another, and ſo ſerving the accuſing, back-biting Spirit: where then is the bridle to thy Tongue? what's thy Religion worth? The Apoſtle tells thee its Vain: <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.26. Thou that art ſuch a one, learn this leſſon, to be <hi>ſwift to hear, ſlow to ſpeak,</hi> as the ſame Apoſtle teaches, <hi>ver.</hi> 19. And know that thou anſwer, not the Light in the Conſciences of others, but they ſee thee in the Light that's in them, and can read thee what thou art when thou art gone. And if thou art a Servant, and pretendeſt to have found the truth of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and to be acquainted with the way of the Lord more perfectly; yet art leſs mindſul of thy buſineſs, and carrys more ſtoutly and faucily towards the Maſters, art more ſtiff to be commanded in thy Service, uſing Religion as a Cloak to withſtand them; and when thou art reproved, retorteſt biting words which may laſh them; thou doſt not anſwer the Light in their Conſciences, which raiſes an expectation in them of more faithful and well-pleaſing Service; thou tranſgreſſes the Counſel of the Lord by his Holy Apoſtles which they delivered to his Servants in the Churches; and thou ſtops their way to the Kingdom of Chriſt, who look for better things to ſpring from the true Spirit, and ſo thou art an offence in the world: And wo to the world becauſe of theſe and ſuch like offences. Therefore, who-ever thou art, Bond or Free, Maſter or Servant, ſee to it, that thy life be upright, and ſingle as before the Lord who ſearches and ſees all thy Actions, and the Intentions of thy heart in them all; and by thy Actions in thy Converſation will diſcover thee to the world; for he that is the Light, giveth them Light to diſcern by.</p>
            <p>And think it not ſufficient that thou art gathered into ſuch a Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and perhaps maiſt have eſteem among them; But conſider that the Kingdom of Heaven is like a net caſt into the Sea, which gathers of every ſort, good and bad: And many things are gathered in the Net that are to be caſt away again; the good only are to be gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into Veſſels, the bad to be caſt away. If therefore thy life be bad, what will thy being gathered into an outward Profeſſion advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage thee? Therefore be not high-minded, becauſe thou art gather<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Net; but fear leſt after thou art gathered, the Profeſſion become a ſnare to thee through diſobedience, for it may become a ſnare to the Rebellious and Stout-hearted, and Diſobedient to the Worldly-minded, to the Hard-hearted and Unmerciful, to the Haughty and Diſdainful, yea, to ſuch as are lifted up and exalted in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:43059:7"/>their own thoughts, and in their own Righteouſneſs, or in any thing elſe (for whatſoever it is that the heart is exalted in, whereby to be lifted up to behave it ſelf proudly above others, its not right before the Lord.) To ſuch, I ſay, whoſe Religion lyes in any forme or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal part of any Profeſſion whatſoever, without an approved Life and Converſation, to ſuch their Table may become a ſnare, and a trap to hold faſt ſuch ſpirits in, while the Lord finds our a purer path for his beloved Seed to travel on in.</p>
            <p>If thou queſtion this, conſider, was not the miniſtration of the Law of <hi>Moſes</hi> given to the <hi>Jews</hi> to feed at, and to be refreſhed at? was it not as a Table ſpread in the Wilderneſs, as well as the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding of outward food for them was? Did not this become a ſnare and a trap to all the Stout-hearted and Hypocritical Profeſſors of it? And ſo they ſtuck faſt in the formal profeſſion of that miniſtration as in a ſnare, when the true humble Seed had joyful tydings brought them, and were tranſplanted into a more ſpiritual and approved way which the Lord directed them to walk in. And doth not the Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> that choſen Veſſel, mind the <hi>Corinthians,</hi> and in them us, That though the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> were Baptized unto <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Cloud, and in the Sea, into that glorious miniſtration (for it was glorious in its time.) Yet for all that, how did their Carkaſſes fall in the Wilderneſs, and never arrived at th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Promiſed Land, the Land of <hi>Canaan?</hi> Now theſe things, ſaith he, happened unto them for en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſamples, and were written for our Admonition, upon whom the ends of the world are come: <hi>Wherefore let him that thinketh he ſtandeth, take heed leſt he fall,</hi> 1 Cor. 10. Again, do but caſt back thine eye, and look upon fore going miniſtrations of latter years, and conſider thy own eſteem of them. Doſt not thou thy ſelf look upon them as a ſnare to many, holding their feet faſt, that they cannot get on in the purſuit of truth, &amp; in following the Lamb whither-ſoever he goes. Now as thou judges of them, it ſhall be judged of thee, except thou walk humbly with thy God, and mindeſt the weighty matters that he chiefly takes delight in. For the Seed is to go forward, and to grow up in thoſe things, and will leave them behind who are found failing therein, although they be ſtrict aſſerters of the outward form of their profeſſion. This is ſpoken to thee that art high &amp; lofty in thy heart, and lifted up above others in thy mind, becauſe of thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion, while as yet thou comes behind ſome of them in thy Life and Converſation; and in actions of Equity and Mercy, and ſuch weighty
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:43059:7"/>things. But to you that are deſpiſed and overlooked by ſuch, to you I ſay, you humble Shrubs, you Under-growth, you Meek and lowly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded ones, whoſe hearts are kept in the fear of God, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by made careful that you offend not in your Life and Converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, nor alſo with the Tongue; and ſo do not make it an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument of ſowing Diſcord or Enmity among Brethren by whiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pering and back-biting (you are as well able to rule the whole body.) Do you keep humble where you are in the lowlineſs of your mind: And if others exalt themſelves over you, and magnifie themſelves in abaſing you, or others, and ſo would bear up themſelves by vilifying others, as if they themſelves were ſome body, and others of light account: Yet be not you like them, neither be troubled that you are hidden and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked; but reſt in the Lord, waiting on his Will, and keeping out of thoſe evils, and recording things in your hearts as you do; and you ſhall be preſerved when many ſeemingly taller Trees ſhall be thrown down with a ſtorm, and their building be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined with a Wave, and thinking to ſtand, ſhall fall; except they come down to you, and repent of the evil of their Tongues, and of the unfaithfulneſs of their Actions and Lives, and of the leaven of Malice and Diſaffection which by their Tongues they ſpread in the hearts of others. For their work is contrary to the work of Chriſt, who laboured with his Father for the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all thoſe that were given to him; but they buſying them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the contrary, are found in that which is abomination to the Lord, <hi>ſowing Diſcord among Brethren,</hi> Prov. 6.16, 19. <hi>And ſtand not clean in that which is to abide in Gods holy Mountain, in that they take up Reproach againſt their Neighbour,</hi> Pſal. 15.1, 3. Therefore their work ſhall fall, and their Building come to nought, and they, except they Repent, ſhall fall under the judgment of others. How oft have I ſeen it fulfilled, That judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing hath turned upon the Heads of thoſe perſons themſelves, who have been forward in judging and condemning others; even as our Lord fore-warned, ſaying, <hi>Judge not, that you be not Judged, for with what Judgment ye Judge, ye ſhall be Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and with what Meaſure ye meet, it ſhall be Meaſured to you again.</hi> Their Religion is vain that cannot bridle the Tongue. And firſt I ask you, <hi>Wherein is it that the true Brother-hood ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:43059:8"/>
            <p>And to you alſo that are of a more circumſpect Behaviour and Converſation, more able to govern the Tongue, and ſo the whole Body, who are not ſo forward to aſperſe others, and are of a more exact life; walking in a more ſtayed Wiſdom; to you, I ſay, ſuffer a Word of Advice from a Friend. Take heed how you give place in your hearts to Reports and Reproaches: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you judg, know certainly, not only the Truth of things repor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, but alſo the ground or reaſon of them, and upon what ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count they are done. For it is a very uncertain way of judging, to judg by the hearing of the Ear, that is by Reports. How hath the whole Nation of the <hi>Jews</hi> been Sealed up under unbelief and hardneſs of heart, by receiving a falſe Report concerning Chriſt; which Report was ſet on foot by ſuch as were of eſteem among the <hi>Jews.</hi> Satan is the ſame ſubtle Adverſary to this day, and knows the Influence of falſe Reports, and miſrepreſentations of things, and how they leaven the hearts of people with preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice one againſt another. And this I teſtifie, that it hinders the ſhedding abroad of the Love of God in their hearts; as on the other hand the preſervation of the pure love one to another tends to the perfecting of the Love of God in us, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 4.12. It was Propheſied of him, whoſe judgment is infallible and uncertain, that he ſhould not judg after the ſight of his eyes (that is by out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward appearance) nor reprove after the hearing of his Ears; but with Righteouſneſs ſhall he judg the Poor, and reprove with E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity for the Meek of the Earth; and he bids us do the ſame; <hi>Judg not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>by outward appearance, but judg Righteous judgment.</hi> The outward appearance of an action may deceive you; the hearing of the Ear by reports may deceive you; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore know not only the truth of a report, nor only the outward appearance; but alſo the ground of an action, and the intention of him that doth it (for that doth much alter the nature of an action before the Lord) leſt you judg him that is not judged of the Lord; and ſo bring the ſame judgment to return back upon your own heads.</p>
            <p>And you that are juſt in your ways, and equal in your dealings, whom no man can charge with Deceit, or Over-reaching, or Falſe dealing in your Affairs of this World, keep ſtedfaſt in your Uprightneſs; and alſo preſs forward, that of Juſt men you
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:43059:8"/>may become Good men; of Juſt men, you may become Merciful men; of Juſt men, you may become Self-denying men. It may be ſome will ſay, What means this? Is not every Juſt man a Good man? Is there any difference between Juſt men and Good men, or between juſt men and Merciful men, and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denying men? I Anſwer, If there were not ſome difference, what means that ſaying of the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.7. <hi>Scarcoly for a Juſt man,</hi> (or <hi>Rightcous man</hi> as its rendred) <hi>will one dye; yet peradventure for a good man ſome would even dare to dye.</hi> Surely when there is ſuch difference in mens affections towards them, there muſt needs be a ſenſible difference between them. Therefore conſider that he is counted a juſt man, that doth not wrong another, though perhaps he will hold faſt what's his own: But he is a Good man, who beſides his juſt equal dealing with others, alſo delights in Mercy and good Eruits, who is of a more free and bountiful good ſpirit; the tenderneſs of whoſe heart to the Diſtreſſed, and good will of his mind to all, carrys him forth to exerciſe Mercy and Bountifulneſs, or Kindneſs to all, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Ability. It may be for ſuch a man, ſome would even dare to dye: So that there is a difference between them: Though the firſt be well approved of, and is a good foundation laid for Mercy to ſpring up from. For if there be not that firſt at the bottom, and ſo things be juſtly come by, let a man give what he will, and for what pious uſes he will, yet it is but Abomination to the Lord, as it is ſaid in the Prophets, <hi>I hate Robbery for Burnt-offerings.</hi> If it be got in a falſe way by Fraud or Oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, though it be dedicated to the uſe of the Lords Service, yet he hates it. So that I ſay, Equity, juſt, upright honeſt dealing muſt needs be at the bottom of every good work that is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted. And where this is laid as a foundation, and Merciful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Kindneſs is built thereupon, this is well-pleaſing before the Lord, and of good report among men.</p>
            <p>Alſo you that are Juſt in your Dealings, let your eye be ſtill forward to come to a further ſtate, even to a more Self-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Spirit among men. I ſhall ſet a Pattern or two of this before you. You have heard (I ſuppoſe) of <hi>Abraham,</hi> who was called by the Lord to leave his own Kindred and Country and to go ſojourn where the Lord ſhould direct him; and he obeyed the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:43059:9"/>Lord therein (being commanded) and went forth he knew not whether; and <hi>Lot</hi> his Brothers Son went with him: and theſe two had both of them very great Subſtance or Riches. And in proceſs of time, their ſubſtance grew ſo great, that they could not dwell together, for the Land was not able to bear them, or ſuſtain their Flocks. And there aroſe a ſtriſe between the Herds<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Cattel, and the Herds-men of <hi>Lots</hi> Cattel. Now behold a pattern for you of Self-denyal in <hi>Abraham.</hi> He was <hi>Lot</hi>'s Unkle, and he followed not <hi>Lot</hi> in his comeing forth of his own Country, but <hi>Lot</hi> followed him; therefore in the caſe of ſtrife, <hi>Lot</hi> ſhould in reaſon, have given way to <hi>Abraham;</hi> and in their ſeparating ſhould have given the choyce to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> which way he would go. But behold <hi>Abraham</hi> denys him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for Peace-ſake, and gives <hi>Lot</hi> the choyce of the Country, <hi>Gen.</hi> 13.8, 9. <hi>Let there be no ſtrife I pray thee</hi> (ſaith he to <hi>Lot) between me and thee, and between my Herd-men and thy Herd-men, for we are Bre hren. Is not the whole Land be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee? Separate thy ſelf I pray thee from me: If thou wilt take the left-hand, then I will go to the right; or if thou wilt take the right hand, then I will go to the left.</hi> Thus Self-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying <hi>Abraham</hi> would ſtand to <hi>Lot</hi>'s leavings.</p>
            <p>Now obſerve a difference in their temper or ſpirit: <hi>Lot,</hi> though he was a juſt man, yet did not ſo yeeld to <hi>Abraham,</hi> as <hi>A raham</hi> yeelded to him. He ſuffered <hi>Lot</hi> to pleaſe himſelf in the choyce of the Country, and <hi>Lot</hi> did pleaſe himſelf, and choſe the beſt of the Country to his underſtanding; <hi>Even the Plains of</hi> Jordan, <hi>where it was well watered every where, even as the Garden of the Lord, and ſo moſt commodious for his Flocks,</hi> Gen. 13.10, 11.</p>
            <p>But what was the Conſequence of <hi>Lots</hi> pleaſing of himſelf, and of <hi>Abrahams</hi> Self-denyal. Obſerve which was the Gainer, which was the Looſer. <hi>Lots</hi> choyce drew him down towards <hi>Sodom,</hi> and at laſt into <hi>Sodom,</hi> where he was once taken Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive together with the <hi>Sodomites,</hi> and all he had led away; and where his Righteous Soul was vexed from day to day, to behold their unlawful deeds; and where at laſt he was in danger to have been burnt with them. <hi>Abraham</hi> on the other hand ſtanding to <hi>Lots</hi> leavings, was ſufficiently recon-penced by the Lord. For the Lord appeared to him after that <hi>Lot</hi> was ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:43059:9"/>from him, and bid him lift up his eyes and look North-ward and South-ward, and Eaſt-ward and Weſt-ward, and promiſes to give him all the Land as far as he could ſee, and to his Seed for a perpetual Inheritance. Beſides this, <hi>Lots</hi> pleaſing of himſelf, ſet him in a place of great danger; <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Self-denyal kept him in ſafety. And the Lord made <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham Lots</hi> Deliverer, firſt from the Captivity of thoſe Kings which took him and all his away with the Spoils of <hi>Sodom;</hi> and afterwards from the burning in which <hi>Sodom</hi> was conſumed: For its ſaid, <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.29. that when God deſtroyed the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the plain. <hi>He remembred</hi> Abraham, <hi>and ſent out</hi> Lot, <hi>out of the mid'ſt of the over-throw, when he over-threw the Cities in which</hi> Lot <hi>dwelt.</hi> Though <hi>Lot</hi> was a juſt man, yet the Lord had more reſpect to <hi>Abraham</hi> in <hi>Lots</hi> deliverance, than to <hi>Lot</hi> himſelf: Such delight had the Lord in Self-deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Abraham.</hi> And theſe words have been often ſounded in my Spirit, <hi>I love juſt</hi> Lots, <hi>but my delight is with the Self-denying</hi> Abrahams. Therefore I lay theſe things before you as a mark for you to preſs forward unto. And they that walk accordingly, though they be counted weak for ſo doing by others who pleaſe their Earthly part in uſing more cunning for the world, yet they ſhall reap the bleſſing from the Lord. I know there is no need of ſpeaking theſe things to ſome, who are taught of the Lord to walk in the ſame ſteps as <hi>Abraham</hi> walked; but nevertheleſs, there be thoſe to whom theſe things may belong, who ſtand in need to be put in mind of them. After the ſame ſteps of <hi>Abraham</hi> did his Son <hi>Iſaac</hi> walk, when there aroſe ſtrife between his Servants and the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> about the Wells he digged, <hi>Gen.</hi> 26. <hi>He ſtill left thoſe that they ſtrove about, to the</hi> Philiſtims, <hi>until he poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſed one without ſtrife, and he called it</hi> Rehoboth, <hi>for now,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>the Lord hath made room for us.</hi> Thus were they taught by the Lord, even to let go that which they had a right to, for Peace-ſake, and to avoyd ſtrife. And thus the true Love teaches where it is riſen in the heart in power. It ſeeks not its own. It's ſo far from encroaching upon anothers right, that it rather gives way to encroachments. Therefore you, in whom this Spirit is found, be not grieved or troubled when
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:43059:10"/>you have to deal with Spirits that are too hard for you in the affairs of this World, becauſe they dare make uſe of more Earthly ſubtilty to compaſs their own ends than you dare do. The Lord that recompenced <hi>Abraham,</hi> will not forget you. Let them that are of a more Earthly Spirit, lay faſt hold of the Earthly things which they love and prefer before ſimplicity of Spirit, but do ye lay hold on the better things, and the Lord will make up your wrongs in due time. For want of this Self-denyal in theſe things, and by giving way to the Earthly mind, and to Covetouſneſs, which is a root of all evil, how many have withered in their ſeveral Profeſſions before us, turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing back to the things which once their faces were turned from.</p>
            <p>And as you ſtand related in Families, be faithful in your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Relations wherein you ſtand. For if you carry diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly therein, that will be as a Worm at the root of whatſoever you can profeſs, and will cauſe all to wither again in whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you may flouriſh. Walk in Love, and in Wiſdom in your places to wards them that are without, not as Fools open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the mouths of the World againſt you for your folly, and then glorying in that, as if it were ſuffering Reproach for the Truth, when it is only for your own headineſs and diſorder. But mind things of good report, as the Apoſtle of our Lord exhorts; that ſo your lives may be of a good ſavour before all, and you may be of good repute among them that are without, and they may glorifie God for you in the day of their Viſitation. But if you be Reproached for the keeping of your Conſciences clear in anſwering the requirings of the Lord, that will turn to your honour and their ſhame that therefore do Reproach you.</p>
            <p>Art thou a Maſter or Miſtreſs in a Family, and art mild and gentle abroad, be ſo at home alſo; not auſtere and fierce, but ruling thy Family in the fear of the Lord, and in Love and meekneſs, inſtructing and directing thoſe under thee; ſo wilt thou be an incouragement to thoſe that ſerve thee. If any be ſtubborn, I do not bid thee lay aſide thy Authority which God hath given thee, but ſee thou uſe it aright as for the Lord. Art thou a Husband, take heed how thou ſuffers thy love to be ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enated
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:43059:10"/>from thy Wife, or gives juſt occaſion to alienate hers from thee. If thou art a Wife, take heed how thou quenches thy Husbands love by thy want of love to him, and be in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to him as thou art commanded, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.1. And let your mutual love to one another, repreſent the Love of Chriſt and his Church, leſt the truth you profeſs above the World, be evil ſpoken of through you.</p>
            <p>You that are Parents, connive not at your Children in evil words; and perverſe and fooliſh actions, whereby they offend others, leſt they grow head ſtrong alſo againſt your ſelves; but in love, and with a holy awe bear down ſuch things in them, retaining a ſence of your love in their hearts; and eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially exalting the Name of the Lord, and his fear in them, that they may receive a good ſavour of the truth, and things per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining unto God, betimes in their youth; and acquaint them with the Scriptures of truth from their Child-hood, as <hi>Timothy</hi> was acquainted; and lay not on Youth more than it is able to bear, neither bring them up in Idleneſs and Sloathfulneſs, nor feed them with ability to follow bad courſes. Set before them an example worthy to be followed, for they mind your example more than your words; and let not your Prayers and Supplications to the Lord, in behalf of your Children be wanting, for the ordering of their hearts is from the Lord. And you Children, be not ſtubborn and ſtiff-necked againſt your Parents, for that's diſhonour to them, and diſobedience to God, being directly contrary to his Will, who hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded you to honour them, and to obey them. Be ſubmiſſive therefore and obedient to them, honouring them by your ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, that (as the Apoſtle of our Lord mindeth you) <hi>Thy days may be long in the Land which the Lord thy God giveth thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And you that are Servants, be faithful in your place, and ſo adorn the Truth which you profeſs. And conſider this well, That you cannot honour what you profeſs, if your humble, ſubmiſſive, obedient, faithful Service to your Maſters, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the fleſh be awanting; for therein chiefly are you eyed by all perſons. And the enquiry of every ones mind after pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſing Perſons (who profeſs more than themſelves) is this.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:43059:11"/>What is ſuch a one in his life? If you be Self-willed, and Stiff, trifling away your time, and neglecting your Maſters buſineſs, or be careleſs and waſtful of things under your hand and cuſtody, and give provoking words to your Maſters when they reprove you, you are out of the path of Truth, what Zeal ſoever you pretend for the Truth. It is not your running or buſie talking for what you profeſs, that will anſwer the Light in the Conſcience of another, ſo as to juſtifie you, if they know that you are negligent, or unfaithful and careleſs in the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time in your Service to your Maſter. Therefore let this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways remain in your minds, That your Service ought to be ſuch, as if you were doing Service to the Lord Chriſt, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever your Maſters be, and whether preſent or abſent. And indeed it is him you ſerve, you that are faithful in your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. And therefore let that bear up your hearts who are found faithful, and yet meet with difficulties and diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from your Maſters. And though they be perverſe and froward, yet be you patient and ſubmiſſive; and that may in time reach their Conſciences, and make them confeſs their evil carriage, and juſtifie you, and ſo honour the Truth which you profeſs. And be not troubled that you are Servants, thinking that if you were free, you would run more ſpeedily in the race ſet before you; for you may bring as much honour to the Lord in your faithfulneſs, and ſubmiſſive ſervice, as if you were free. Diligence and Providence in buſineſs, and mindfulneſs that nothing go to waſt and ruine under ones hand, if they be free, it's look't upon as for ones ſelf; but in Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice to another, it's more look't upon as from the fear of the Lord ruling your hearts, and more convincing to others that the Lord is with you. Set before you the example of <hi>Jacob,</hi> who ſerved <hi>Laban</hi> thrice ſeven years faithfully, though <hi>Laban</hi> dealt deceitfully with him, <hi>and changed his Wages ten times,</hi> Gen. 31.7. <hi>J. cob,</hi> for all that being faithful, the Lord bleſſed his Labours, and increaſed <hi>Labans</hi> Flock abundantly for <hi>Jacobs</hi> ſake, and made <hi>Laban</hi> ſenſible thereof, and confeſs it, <hi>Gen.</hi> 30.27. <hi>I find by experience,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that the Lord hath bleſſed me for thy ſake.</hi> Oh ſtrive to be ſuch Servants as may have the bleſſing of the Lord to go along with your Service, to the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:43059:11"/>convinceing of thoſe you ſerve, as you ſee it was with <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And as it was with <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſo alſo with <hi>Joſeph</hi> his Son, when he was Servant in <hi>Egypt</hi> to <hi>Potipher. The Lord made all that was under his hand to proſper,</hi> as you may read <hi>Gen.</hi> 39. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by his Maſter ſaw that the Lord was with him. And do not think theſe Examples to be too high to be look't at by you that are Servants, as if it were beyond expectation to attain to the like. For there is a like bleſſing promiſed to every one, and attends every one that are found faithful, delighting in the Law of the Lord, <hi>and Meditating therein Day and Night,</hi> Pſal. 1.3. And if you ſay, you have not that Wiſdom which they had; <hi>If any man want Wiſdom, let him ask it of God, and he will give Wiſdom where there is endeavour to pleaſe him.</hi> And ſeeing the Lord hath diſpoſed the whole Earth (which is as a great Houſe that he takes care of) into Families; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Servants are as needful in their places, as Maſters in theirs. And as to your ſpiritual Eſtate and Son-ſhip, and your Eternal happineſs, there is no reſpect of perſons with God. Therefore may Servants go on as cheerfully in their work of ſubmiſſive Obedience, as Maſters in theirs of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding and Ruling. Be not therefore troubled that thou art a Servant, but be contented in that Condition, untill thou ſeeſt Providence leading thee forth as <hi>Jacob</hi> was. And Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters be not Cruel and Tyrannical, or Unjuſt to your Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, or like <hi>Pharoahs</hi> Task maſters to them, but conſider them as of the ſame fleſh and blood with your ſelves; and alſo that they are or may be Heirs of the Kingdom of God as well as you. And therefore uſe them as you would be uſed, if you were in their place.</p>
            <p>And let every one that profeſſes the Name of the Lord, mind the blameleſs life that becomes Chriſtianity. This therefore I ſay, <hi>That the Life of a Chriſtian is a Plain, Humble, Meek, Innocent, Juſt, Merciful, Faithful, Sober, Temperate, Gentle, Loving, Kind, Chaſt, Contented, Wiſe, Peaceable, Holy, Diligent, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pright, Harmleſs, Inoffenſive Life and Converſation; Chaſt alſo to God as well as to Man:</hi> For the right Chriſtian doth Worſhip God in Spirit and in Truth,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:43059:12"/>and will not proſtitute his Soul to the known Superſtitious Worſhips of Mans Wiſdom and ordering, which was always counted ſpiritual Whoredom with God: In ſuch a Life, or in purſuance thereof, doth the true Chriſtian live.</p>
            <p>The Ground of this Chriſtian life is from the Spirit of the Lord working in man, and changing the heart (though ſome know it not) and inclining it to theſe things which the Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and Faithful do walk in. And the Lord knoweth his own, who are of an upright heart, though they as yet know not him, but may doubt of their knowing of him, as <hi>Philip</hi> did. But continuing in his Fear, and abiding in the Path of Righteouſneſs and Holineſs, they may come to know the Lord, and that it is he that Operates all theſe things in them, and for them; and to feel the cleanſing and waſhing of their Conſciences by the Blood of Jeſus Chriſt from all ſin; which is enjoyed in walking in the Light, but not in talking of it only.</p>
            <p>The true Chriſtian Life doth not lye in words; as if to be changed from one form of words to another, were it; al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Holy Spirit which changeth the heart require words ſutable to himſelf; and to eſchew corrupt words. Neither doth it lye in the changing of Apparrel; although the Spirit that changeth require modeſt Apparrel, ſutable to himſelf, and ſutable to that humble mind which he formeth in man.</p>
            <p>Nor doth it ſtand in high Notions, or ſoaring Imaginations, (wherein the exalted nature gets up and magnifies it ſelf above the ſimple-hearted,) but it is in ſimplicity and godly ſincerity. With ſuch exalted Spirits the Apoſtles of our Lord were much troubled in the Primitive times after Chriſt, and laboured much to keep down Believers from them, to the ſimplicity that was in Chriſt, as you may perceive by their Epiſtles. Of ſuch alſo our Lord made mention, and ſtrengthened the ſimple-hearted againſt them, in ſome of his Epiſtles to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia.</hi> In that to <hi>Thyatira,</hi> he takes notice of ſome who were high in their Imaginations and Notions; inſomuch that they looked upon thoſe whom the Lord approved of, but as weak and low in compariſon of themſelves, and as ſuch as did
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:43059:12"/>not know the depths of Satan; for that was the phraſe it ſeems which they uſed. But the Lord encouraged the ſimple-heart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed againſt their exalted expreſſion, and ſaid, <hi>I will lay on you no other burthen; but that which you have already, hold faſt till I come,</hi> Rev. 2.24, 25. And what would he do when he comes? that he had expreſſed before, <hi>verſe</hi> 23. <hi>I will give to every one according to his Works;</hi> not according to their Imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</p>
            <p>Neither doth the life of Chriſtianity ſtand in any outward formal way, although ſome way may be required for the gathering together of the true Worſhippers, who Worſhip in Spirit and in Truth. As its probable there was in the old World before the Flood; for there was a diſtinction between the Sons of God, and thoſe that were called the Daughters of Men. Some were called Men, and ſome the Sons of God. But how-ever, after the Flood it is expreſly ſaid, <hi>Job.</hi> 1.6. <hi>That the Sons of God came together to preſent themſelves before the Lord.</hi> So that this may be requiſite, and hath been practiſed, more eſpecially in all ages ſince Chriſtianity was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly named in the World. But obſerve, Satan himſelf can come there as well as the Sons of God. The <hi>Phariſee</hi> can be there, whoſe Religion lyes chiefly, if not only in outward ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervances. For the Proud, Covetous, Perſecuting, Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſaical, Hypocritical ſpirit can come under the formal part of any Profeſſion. And ſo there were thoſe in the Apoſtles days who had a form of Godlineſs, but denying the power thereof, they were to be turned away from. For their lives were corrupt, as you may read, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. where you may ſee of what ſort they were.</p>
            <p>Neither doth it ſtand in openings or viſions of things, or underſtanding of Myſteries, though theſe are excellent gifts given forth from the Lord, and enjoyed by many of his Faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Ones. Yet for as much as evil Men and Spirits may have true Opinions, therefore the Life of a Chriſtian doth not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt therein, but in living in Obedience unto the pure Life which doth open. <hi>Balaam</hi> had very eminent Viſions and Openings of things, yet is he Noted in Scripture for a falſe Prophet, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:43059:13"/>his Heart, and ſo his Life was not right before the Lord. His heart run after the reward of Unrighteouſneſs, and he gave evil Counſel to <hi>Balaac</hi> againſt a People whom he knew the Lord had reſpect to, and would not ſuffer him to ſpeak an evil word of them to <hi>Balaac;</hi> yet he taught <hi>Balaac</hi> to entice them to Fornication and Idolatry. Satan himſelf, and the evil Spirits may have openings, and a ſence given them of true things as its plain they had in the days of Chriſt in the fleſh: <hi>Art thou come,</hi> ſaid they, <hi>to torment us before the time?</hi> They knew that by him God would judge the World and them; and they knew the time was not yet: <hi>Therefore,</hi> ſay they, <hi>art thou come to do that Work before the time?</hi> They knew whence he was, &amp; what he was: <hi>We know thee, who thou art, ſaid they, even the Holy One of God. Paul</hi> and <hi>Silas</hi> going about in the Miniſtery of the Lord, the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil Spirits knew them, and followed them, crying, <hi>Theſe are the Servants of the Living God,</hi> Act. 16.17. &amp; chap. 19.15. Jeſus <hi>I know, and</hi> Paul <hi>I know, but who are ye</hi> ſaid the evil Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit to the <hi>Exorciſts,</hi> who took upon them to caſt out Devils in the Name of Jeſus. And further, <hi>Satan knoweth when his time is near an end, and that he hath but a ſhort time,</hi> Rev. 12.12. Therefore in reſpect of theſe things be wiſe to Sobriety, and mind the approved blameleſs Life: And let not Satan diſquiet and trouble you, becauſe you are not as ſuch a one, or ſuch a one, who have had wonderful Openings from the Lord; but keep down to the Anointing, that abiding unction which guides the Life, and diſcovers evil Paths, and leads into all Truth, and keeps abiding in the Truth, and abiding in the Lord.</p>
            <p>I do highly prize the ſerviceable gifts of knowledge and utte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and ſuch like, given for the ſervice of others: But the Union of my heart is with you that are careful, that you of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend not in your words, nor in your lives, who walk humbly with your God, obſerving the checks, motions, inclinations of the Spirit of Chriſt in your hearts; applying to the Lord in all caſes, eſpecially of difficulty, as a Child to the Father, for Council, Guidance, Wiſdom, Strength, Aſſidance, Succour, Succeſs; whoſe Holy Spirit is your Guide, Strength, Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:43059:13"/>in Prayers and Supplications, and Thankſgivings, without limitation to time, or place, ſo that you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be baniſhed from your Temple or place of Worſhip, or removed into a corner where you cannot offer up Spiritual Sacrifices to God. You whoſe hearts do breath after the Lord, and to be filled with his Holy Nature; and you who inwardly Converſe with God, dwelling in inward Peace and Conſolation which the World cannot give, nor take away, it being Adminiſtred by him whom they cannot reach: You, whoſe hearts are ballanced with the free gift of God to your ſelves, that excludes all boaſting, and with the true ſenſe of the Univerſal Love of God over all, that ſhuts out all Phariſaical ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>altation, and deſpiſing of others, and ſo are kept lowly in your minds. Alſo you who mournt in ſecret, who Hunger and Thirſt after Righteouſneſs, to be filled with it your ſelves; and that it may fill the Earth. Such as you it is that my heart is towards, from the leaſt of you that have the true ſavour of God in your hearts, to the greateſt, from the Babe to the Father. It's you that my Soul longs after, whereſoever you are found walking at preſent. And that ſuch may be daily raiſed up more abundantly to the magnifying of the Name of the Lord in the Earth, and to the convincing of the World of the evil of their ways, and of a Righteous Life, that their hearts may be opened thereby to believe the Truth, and to receive it in the Love of it, is the earning of my Soul. For theſe are they which are the true Seed of <hi>Sion,</hi> of which glorious things are ſpoken, and which the Lord loves above all the dwellings of <hi>Judah,</hi> above all the out-works or formal ways of all profeſſions. It's you that honour the Lord, and make his Name to be loved in the Earth.</p>
            <p>And your Prayers do I deſire on my behalfe (as mine are for you) that utterance, and ſtrength, and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſs may be given me, to hold forth the Truth ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:43059:14"/>and ſtedfaſtly, both in Life and Doctrine, as it is, or may be communicated unto me.</p>
            <p>And to you, the God of peace multiply all bleſſings with Joy and Conſolation, and make you to abound more and more in every good gift to his praiſe, and to the raiſing up of thirſtings after Righteouſneſs in the hearts of others,</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb facs="tcp:43059:14"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>IF this ſhall fall into the hands of any that have an Enmity in them againſt the Flock, and therefore catch at every fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing they can eſpy, or hear of in any Member, that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they may aſperſe the whole: Let them know, that firſt of all, they ought to judge at home, and learn to ſeparate between the Precious and the Vile in their own Boſom, and then will they come to diſtinguiſh after the ſame manner in the Flocks of Chriſt; and their deſire and endeavour will be rather to convince thoſe that err, and ſtrengthen thoſe that are weak, and gather thoſe that ſtray, and ſupport thoſe that ſtumble, and help forward thoſe that come behind, and to hide the Infirmities of the weak, then ſeek to blaſt the whole by the weakneſs or wickedneſs of ſome. Let ſuch remember the words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah, Woe to him that calls good evil, or evil, good; that puts darkneſs for light, and light for darkneſs, and ſo confounds what God would have diſtinguiſhed.</hi> The true Spirit is not a Spirit of Confuſion, but of Order and Clearneſs, diſtinguiſhing aright between the Preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and Vile. And ſo did our Lord teach us to do by his example in his Epiſtle ſent to the ſeven Churches of <hi>Aſia;</hi> the good that was found in them he approved of, and encouraged, and reproved only the evil. He did not over-look the good in them, becauſe of the evil; neither did he approve of the evil becauſe of the good; but ſaith he, I have ſomewhat againſt thee, <hi>Repent,</hi> &amp;c. Let us learn to be like-minded, leſt any one by falſe and confuſed judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, heap Judgment and Condemnation upon their own Heads.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>W. T.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
